hello and welcome it's July 26th 2023
we're here in octave inference live
stream for 9.1 with Megan Peters and
Nora Bradford so thank you both for
joining we're looking forward to a
presentation followed by a discussion on
clickbait Consciousness science and
responsible journalism so back in to you
thank you and thanks so much Daniel for
having us we're really happy to be here
uh and to chat about this so I'll talk
for a little over 10 minutes and then
we'll hopefully have a nice discussion
here
um so yeah we're really happy to be here
because I think that this is a really
topical uh really
um yeah very topical thing for us to be
talking about right now it's very in the
media it's really in response to the way
the media has been covering
Consciousness science just in the past
few weeks uh so here here we go I'll
have a few things to share with you okay
so since we're talking about
Consciousness science
um let's start with a provocative
question so you are conscious
how is this possible
how is it possible that your brain
creates the conscious experience of you
and so this is a captivating and it's a
stimulating kind of crazy question it's
a really huge question uh borders on the
religious and spiritual in many ways it
borders on The Cutting Edge of physics
in many ways and so the study of this
question and the field of Consciousness
science more generally it's really
straddling the border between the
Natural Sciences and philosophy and
spirituality in a way that a lot of
other domains maybe don't need to do and
so as a result this field of
Consciousness science it really captures
the hearts and and minds and sometimes
pretty wild imaginations of all sorts of
folks as I said from psychologists and
biologists and neuroscientists all the
way to computer scientists and Engineers
to religious and spiritual leaders
basically anybody who wonders about our
origins or place in the universe why
that we know that we are here why there
is something that it is like to be us
they are the people who are interested
in this question and that's probably a
lot of people who are listening and
watching right now so it's it's actually
really quite easy I think to get swept
up in The Sensational nature of this
question and Consciousness science is a
really big deal it touches on so many
aspects of our everyday experience
um and so this kind of leads us to
another version of this question which
is is this even really science is this
something that can be even studied
scientifically or does it transcend
Beyond on scientific inquiry did
Consciousness scientists do something
that can be characterized really as
science or maybe they're studying
something that's a little bit more on
the border like I don't know telepathy
or pan psychism like maybe rocks and
trees are also conscious wouldn't that
be crazy or maybe the vibrations of the
use mean that the universe is conscious
so it it kind of quickly starts to feel
a little a little fuzzy a little less
scientific
um and that's what I want to talk about
today is that perception and how that is
kind of exacerbated by the way that this
field is portrayed in the media and
maybe what we can do about it
um okay and so all this means that the
conscience and science is really
difficult not just to do scientifically
and it is really difficult I promise you
um but it's also really difficult from a
social perspective so more than than for
some other fields those of us who who do
Consciousness science and who study this
scientifically we have a really crucial
and difficult responsibility which is to
accurately and precisely communicate the
state of our field and its methods and
its discoveries and how it relates to
other fields from physics to medicine
and and Beyond
um and it's in fact so difficult that
our field has actually written a number
of papers about just how difficult it is
so um this is a fairly recent paper
always included in many other
um and this is just from a few years ago
and uh these papers and this one in
particular really highlight why our
field in in uh specific has kind of an
uphill battle compared to a lot of other
areas of study especially when it comes
to potential misrepresentation in the
media so I thought that maybe in order
to drive this point home I could
actually give you some examples of how
subconsciousness science has been
misrepresented in the media so that we
can get a handle on this we can see it
concretely and as I'm giving you some of
these examples I want you to to try to
imagine how it would sound if the same
kinds of statements the same kind of
sweeping claims were made about
discoveries in biology or chemistry
Neuroscience climate science engineering
that kind of thing all right so let's do
some examples here is the first one okay
and this is an example which is actually
13 years old at this point um as well as
I think you'll see maybe it hasn't
gotten so much better over the past 13
years but in this example the title
sizing of Consciousness by its bits we
have Christoph Coke who is an expert on
Consciousness science at Caltech being
quoted as saying I love his ideas it's
the only real promising fundamental
Theory and here
is deciding to present just this one
scientist's opinion as fact without
challenging it all without presenting
any other opinions at all I'll point out
that this opinion was actually not
representative of the consensus in the
field at that time it was this one
scientist's point of view and it's not
actually representative of the consensus
in the field now either and so I want
you to take this quote but I want you to
replace Consciousness with curing cancer
so this opinion presented as fact is
akin to writing that one scientist's
theory about a cure for cancer is the
only really promising fundamental theory
for curing cancer
and without presenting any other
possibilities that that maybe more work
needs to be done or more more
experiments need to be run this is
really hyperbolic and it seems like
maybe this kind of hyperbole would be
hopefully at least a little less likely
to happen in biomedicine or at least
with receive more more pushback if it
were presented this way
so here's another example and this one's
a bit more recent so this one's from um
2018.
uh
just
is
okay so the electrical activity that
moves across neurons is thought by some
scientists to contribute to human
consciousness this is like a perfectly
reasonable statement right like totally
fine totally legit but then the
journalist goes on to say if electrical
activity is being disrupted by
anesthetic and plants two causing them
to lose Consciousness does that mean in
some way that they are conscious
okay so first of all these statements
are are pretty vague um that's not
really super surprising from a popular
science piece and it's not really the
the primary problem here saying that a
liberty that moves across neurons
thought to
distance
from destruction of electrical activity
to plants being conscious
and this is pretty Sensational kind of
to the extreme and it makes this fuzzy
border between Consciousness science and
pseudoscience which is this border that
we are trying so hard to delay all the
time
it makes it even fuzzier gives us an
even harder problem to fight against as
Consciousness and it isn't Just
Happening 13 years ago five years ago it
still has like if I were talking
just last uh there was this post which
was held in conjunction with the
association for the scientific study of
Consciousness annual meeting which was
in New York City and at this public
event Christoph Coke who you can see
here on the right and Dave Chalmers
here's on the left they presented their
25 year old bet about whether the neural
correlates of Consciousness the ones
that go up and down with Consciousness
goes up and down uh would be found
later
and during this public event some new
results were unveiled for the very first
time from one of the ongoing projects
which was designed to challenge two of
the many theories about how
Consciousness arises in the brain and
those two theories are called the global
neuronal workspace Theory and the
integrated information Theory and the
hot off the press results that were
shown in this event uh they actually
ended up challenging both theories they
showed that the neural correlates of
Consciousness are still unknown that
neither theory was really strongly
supported by the data that were
collected and so on but that's not the
story that's not exciting and so that's
not the story that the Press told and so
here is what the media actually said
okay so first we're going to start with
nature
nature the journalism side of this
Flagship scientific journal you'd hope
that they would be pretty careful about
their scientific journalism but instead
they write taglines like this like
Kristoff wager Dave 25 years ago the
researchers would learn how the brain
achieves Consciousness by now
um but the quest continues but this is
actually not what the BET was about but
that was about the neural correlates not
the causal mechanisms not the generative
production of Consciousness and remember
not the same thing and there's always a
relevant XKCD and so I direct you to
this one here
um but it gets worse so here's what
science science had to say
um Advocates of the losing idea are not
conceding yet
so again neither idea lost remember or
rather both of them lost neither one of
them won nobody lost nobody won
um and so why would science say that one
of them lost or is even losing it seems
a little over the top and so it kind of
makes you wonder are they like trying to
drive clicks or what what is the point
here of sensationalizing quite to this
degree it seems like a bad idea it seems
like oversimplification that actually
changes the meaning of of what was
presented
so here's another example this is from
The Economist
um this article largely reported on a
different event that was actually part
of the assc like primary meeting but it
still capitalized on the the buzz that
this public event this evening event
created
um and it opens with this really kind of
terrible Twist of the actual
experimental design so the economist
article says top of the bill was the
announcement of the result of a
so-called adversarial collaboration
between proponents of two hypotheses
about the nature of Consciousness again
not what the BET was about it wasn't
about the nature of Consciousness but
anyway
um this involved running a series of
experiments begun in 2020 to determine
which if either of them is correct
again that's not what the collaboration
was designed to do right in science you
can never prove anything you can never
show you're correct you can only show
that you are not wrong or that you are
wrong that's it that's what you get in
science
okay
so
moreover all of these articles the three
that I've shown you and a number of
others
um they also contained essentially no
discussion of whether these two theories
Global neuronal workspace Theory and
integrated information Theory one of
which was losing apparently
um whether they were the only ones worth
considering so the Articles didn't
really discuss anything else any other
possible theories in fact the the
Articles called these two theories
leading by the media but the truth is
that they're leading only in number of
Publications not an amount of scientific
evidence supporting them they just have
a lot of Publications out there there's
no discussion in these articles Beyond a
trivial passing mention that there are
any other theories out there at all and
especially that they are not whether
they are viable or not whether they're
empirically supported so here's some
this isn't all of the empirically
supported theories of Consciousness out
there there's a really nice article here
by Anil and Tim uh Anil Seth and Tim
Bain that came out last year that
discusses a bunch of these and there's a
really nice article here
um by this group also saying they
actually looked at the empirical support
for different theories of Consciousness
how many papers are out there that
actually challenge versus support each
Theory and so this landscape is the one
that should be the one to evaluate all
of the results that were presented at
this event in it means that even if one
of the two theories that this one
project was looking at if one of them
didn't make the cut that doesn't mean
the other one wins and is right it just
means that one of them may be lost and
it didn't even lose remember
in fact so in addition to these really
nice papers
uh there's also a whole series of these
adversarial collaborations from the same
funding agency as the one that was shown
in his public event that are designed to
actually pit these theories against each
other in a pairwise fashion in a like
Thunderdome style for All You Mad Max
fans out there I love old school sci-fi
and the idea here is that two theories
enter and one Theory leaves one Theory
survives but it doesn't win because
there's another round coming
and so all of these nuances they were
just unfortunately missing from all the
news coverage and I understand that news
likes to get people to read it and it
likes to be Sensational but the missing
aspects of these new the missing Nuance
really changes the meaning of what was
presented and that's actually a really
big problem here
uh and why is this such a problem you
might ask I'm getting myself all worked
out here right
um so the answer to why I'm getting all
worked up really comes back to what I
presented in the beginning which is that
we Consciousness scientists have this
uphill battle we constantly have to
fight to legitimize our research program
and importantly this isn't just in the
eyes of the public so it's not just in
the eyes of the people reading these
articles who are not part of this
scientific sphere it's also in the eyes
of the scientific Community more
generally of our funding agencies and
maybe most importantly our close peers
within adjacent Fields so imagine for a
second that you are on a hiring
committee at a university and you read a
candidate's description of their
research program and it is about
Consciousness science
okay they have pages and pages and
several Publications and they maybe have
a grant that's about Consciousness
science but you as the member of the
hiring Committee just read this this New
York Times article about how plants
probably have consciousness
and so maybe your eyes are now rolling
out of your head because you've been
primed to think this isn't real this is
Sensational this isn't something that
can be studied scientifically you might
as well be talking about doing research
on telepathy is this really a colleague
that you want
so here's another example what if you're
on a grant Review Committee or you're
reviewing a paper
and you just read these articles in
science and in nature that heavily imply
that there are only two real theories of
Consciousness that have any empirical
support
but the paper or grant that you're
reviewing is not targeting either one of
these theories
so now maybe you see the problem here
these journalism articles they're
they're not just infuriating they're
really actively damaging the legitimacy
of our field they're cutting us off at
the knees in the eyes of our peers in
terms of the financial support we can
compete for from granting agencies in
terms of where we can publish our
science and by the way that science is
state of the art and cutting edge
we have a responsibility though as
people who are doing the
state-of-the-art Consciousness science
to try to work with the media so that
the reporting can be more honest so you
know we can continue working there as
well this is a two-way street in some
ways but we also hope that folks who are
listening right now will recognize this
pattern the next time you read an
article about Consciousness science then
maybe those sensationalized claims are
not exactly a reflection of the state of
Art and in the field because here's the
truth
this is real Consciousness science
modern Consciousness science it's a
collection of basically every single
state of the art discipline and method
of scientific inquiry that you can think
of so my version of Consciousness
science that I do in my lab is a
conglomeration of cognitive sciences and
computational Neuroscience and a little
bit of computer science artificial
intelligence machine learning thrown in
we also have heavy influences from
philosophy and psychology and
engineering and a little bit of meta
science and we have neuroimaging we have
statistics and this is really a
representation of Consciousness science
not just in my research group but the
conscious of science being done
worldwide by thousands of people
conscious that science is right at the
center right at the heart the very
bleeding edge of our Collective
scientific understanding
um so
remember when I put this slide up before
and I said that the study of this
question straddles the border between
Natural Sciences and philosophy in a way
that a lot of other domains maybe don't
need to do and as a result it captures
our imagination it gets out there it
gets into your brain and your mind and
sticks there in a way that some other
fields might not
but maybe you can see through what I've
talked about today that the challenge is
uh with communicating the Crux of this
question and in doing the science itself
that actually makes the people who are
doing this pretty brave especially the
younger trainees when you think about it
they're fighting this real uphill battle
so personally me I'm relatively safe I
have job security if people don't take
me seriously when I say I'm a conscious
scientist that's their loss that's fine
you know but the younger people the
trainees in the field those who are
trying to get jobs those who are trying
to to push the envelope of what we know
about our brains and our minds and our
awareness of ourselves in in this world
they've got a lot of misperceptions to
overcome uh so if you are excited and
you want to know more about the modern
exciting field of Consciousness science
I suggest that you head to the assc
website you can have a look at the whole
Science Program they've actually posted
videos of the Keynotes from this year so
that's pretty cool you can go and see
some of those
um they can you can also check out the
plan for the future
um and of course if I've inspired you
even a little bit to find out about
Consciousness science yourself despite
my kind of Grant here
um I say welcome please come join us
there's a lot of people doing some
really cool stuff really amazing
mind-blowing stuff working to figure
this out so please come join us
absolutely the more the merrier uh and
so I think I will stop there and just
say if you've enjoyed uh this talk or or
anything that I said resonated with you
I've got a real short little piece here
it's about 800 words so not a long
homework assignment you can go and check
that out
um so I think I'll stop and pass the mic
back to Daniel and also welcome Nora
Bradford who is a doctoral student here
at UC Irvine who works in Consciousness
science but who also is an accomplished
science journalist and he's written
articles in Scientific American Science
News discover and many more so thanks
very much
awesome
wow
cool Dora baby to you for our first
reflection about what what you see there
or how you came to be here yeah sure
um yeah so I was at assc and went to the
event
um that was associated with assc but not
run by ascc just to be clear
um and it was really exciting to see
Continental science kind of being
celebrated in the way that it was I had
some issues with the event but overall
like I was very excited that it was
getting this like public attention right
um and then afterwards I was again like
excited to see that people were writing
about my field because
that doesn't happen
I'm like I could do
um like immediately kind of disappointed
by not wrong
um
yeah and I guess I started to think
about kind of why conscious science is
maybe a harder
journalist to cover and I think there is
just probably a lot more controversy and
a lot more room for mistakes to be made
um then perhaps in fields where the
research is more clear-cut or more
easily interpretable
um so yeah I think there's a lot as
journalists and also as researchers from
this
yeah I'll um can I can I just really
probably follow up and say I I think
that Nora you're spot on by saying that
uh it's or by
presenting the idea that it's it's the
interpretation that's part of the
problem here it's not just that people
are maybe getting facts wrong when
they're writing about this field it's
that the interpretations are really
nuanced they're really difficult to get
right and it's really easy for an
oversimplification to end up
fundamentally changing the meaning in
this space in a way that maybe doesn't
occur quite as often in some other
fields
yeah that that's really interesting to
kind of disentangle the features that
that make this a unique although also
exemplary case of communicating
challenging ideas I mean the first that
presents itself to me is just how much
is on the table I mean whose pain
matters whose experiences or what
experiences even matter what's the
difference between a who and a what this
is the real question if something
doesn't have an experience
then there's no feeling but if something
does have an experience then it's it's a
feeling and it's a morally
um culpable or
um something that we're responsible for
treating in an ethical way so it's like
whether or not it's always brought up in
those articles the stakes are so high
whereas whether a given molecular
compound does this molecular interaction
is closer to the objective whereas this
is the ultimate subjective
questions seemingly
sure yeah I I agree with you definitely
that the ethical Stakes the the moral
implications of this field are are just
staggering and certainly there it's not
unique in that that way that the ethical
and moral implications of sociological
research or climate science or you know
of many other domains also have like
these staggering implications
um I think one of the the biggest
challenges that we have is not just in
the interpretation of objective data but
exactly as you've just said this is the
ultimate subjectivity that the thing
that we are studying by its definition
is not objectively observable
and that is absolutely something that is
uh at least you can design measurement
Tools in a way that have different
philosophical foundations in basically
every other field but by its very Nature
by the definition of subjective
experience we cannot design a
measurement tool that actually says what
is it like to be you that's kind of the
whole problem
but your your uh
your points also about the ethical
implications in medicine the difference
between a who and a what um I think that
that's also really important to bring it
outside here we are trying to to you
know I presented this as like we want to
understand Consciousness and I never
really defined consciousness he just
said like here's Consciousness and like
here's an umbrella term and you you take
that kind of how you want
um but it's true that Consciousness
science spans all the way from you know
wakefulness versus coma uh or locked in
syndrome or traumatic brain injury
um anesthesia all the way through to uh
is a baby conscious is a fetus conscious
is an AI conscious is a cockroach all
right or your dog uh or you know 200
years ago people might argue that
children were less conscious than adults
and so it was okay to hit your children
because they wouldn't feel it as much or
something and so there's there's a lot
of sociological and ethical and moral
implications in everything that we're
doing
which is why
one of the reasons I've chosen this
field too is that it really scratches a
lot of intellectual itch but it also
feels really important especially right
now with the rise of machine
intelligence and with uh ongoing debates
about animal uh or fetal Consciousness
that really bear
extreme impact on legislation on you
know moral decisions that we make as a
people so yeah it's it's a big thing
that we're doing
I'm a little biased but it is a big
thing
and I would add that even if researchers
are sometimes good at explaining what
they mean by Consciousness in their
research like two journalists say the
journalists are not always necessarily
great at communicating that to the
public for their writing
um and I get why that would be hard it's
kind of it can be fun it can be like
awkward and unappealing to explain but
that is crucial because people readers
can take it however they want based on
how they're interpreting the word
Consciousness
um so I think that's super important to
address if you're writing about
consciousness
yeah it's really a field that's kind of
a a leading indicator
because
especially if approached in a scientific
way
in our current setting uh a scientific
understanding of X is what shapes
evidence-driven policy about X so I
guess this leads to what what is or or
would or could be a science-driven
approach like how do we know it when we
see it when someone is approaching this
question from a scientific perspective
what would what would each of you say to
this
well I'm going to give kind of the stock
answer which is that you want to have
objective measures that are valid and
reliable
um but the the big one is falsifiability
and that's you know any student of
science going back to grade school is
going to learn a little bit about that
which is that if you've got a theory or
you've got a hypothesis uh about how
let's say the brain uh generates
Consciousness or even going back to just
correlates just like which bits of the
brain are are
correlated in their activity with
whether you're more conscious or less
conscious so let's keep it really like
very basic
um you need to have it be falsifiable
you need to have say it's this area of
the brain that will correlate and not
that area of the brain or that uh and
the recognition that an absence of
evidence is not evidence of absence is
also really crucial to this idea which
is that just because I failed to measure
a correspondence between the activity
and the bit of the brain that I
hypothesized and you know some measure
of awareness that I get from self-report
doesn't mean that that area of the brain
isn't doing the work it just means that
our machines are terrible or that our
measure sucks
um and and honestly despite the
state-of-the-art measurements that we do
have we have you know millimeter level
Precision in humans we have cellular
level precision and non-human animals we
can record a lot of stuff
um
and we have a lot of really fancy
machine learning algorithms to help us
extract what that stuff means
to go from super high dimensional noisy
data down to something that we can maybe
make the argument is interpretable
uh inter interpretable yeah
um but
just because you didn't find what you
were looking for doesn't mean that it's
not there it just means that you were
maybe looking in the wrong place or that
you were looking using the wrong tool
uh and so these these kind of go hand in
hand because on the one hand you want
your hypothesis to be falsifiable so you
aren't allowed to just say oh well I
just wasn't looking for it the right way
so I'm just gonna you know revise how
I'm looking and try again and therefore
I'm still right
you need to design your experiments and
your theories such that if you find a
particular result a positive result that
it actually disproves your theory as
opposed to just failing to provide
support for your theory
um so I think that those those those and
you know other kind of standard criteria
that you might find in any stem
classroom that demonstrate the
scientific method uh those are probably
the the definitions that I would fall
back on and I think that Consciousness
and science broadly speaking the stuff
that is presented in assc it does all of
that
um it absolutely does it's the same
caliber of computational Neuroscience
and neuroimaging and psychological
psychophysics measurement and logical
philosophy approaches that you would
find at any other Flagship conference in
the in the world yeah
and I would say if you're reading
um an article rather than like a journal
paper like if you're reading something
in the in the Press
um the way to know if it's trustworthy
or not or one way is if it's making
Sensational claims like claiming to have
you know found the root of Consciousness
or some really large claim it's probably
not true like I think we would that
wouldn't happen in one study I'm
assuming um so just read with a
skeptical eye and
um if you feel comfortable try to read
the primary Literature Like get inspired
by the the Press but if you feel like
there's something off just go to the
primary literature and see what's up and
and see if you can interpret for
yourself it's understandable if you can
but
yeah that's what I would say that's a
good rule of thumb Nora that like one
study is never going to be the answer
yeah not just ours but it's it's easy to
get swept away in The Sensational claims
and to be like ooh they found like the
neural cause of Consciousness like
probably not yeah yeah and I would say
like pre-registration also I mean Megan
I don't know like what your rule of
thumb is for this but those I mean if
people pre-register there
um you know plan for the study and how
they're going to analyze it ahead of
time that is usually a really good sign
I mean basically what you're just saying
but just like stamp of we promise we did
this ahead of time kind of thing
um yeah avoids parking
lotsizing after the fact right yeah
yeah it was kind of cool to see Meta
science
um
and also maybe kind of a
bibliographic analyzes looking at
different Trends in literature but then
also going beyond the peer-reviewed
literature to looking at the real trends
that that influence people who are
outside of the profession and it's like
um it's kind of I don't know if Canary
in the coal mine is the right
um birds in the right Niche here but
it's like
um proposing unobservables
is commonplace in research like latent
cause analysis and and any kind of
structural equation modeling
and here is the um
the tour de force of unobservables maybe
that which is defined as unobservables
and so it's actually like a space to to
bring up all these pieces of epistemic
hygiene about from pre-registration to
the PACE and the tone of the scientific
community and questions of like
multi-disciplinarity in research it's
it's kind of um it's a fun and then
there's a heart at the intersection of
the Venn diagram where it kind of all
comes together it's like well this
synthesis cannot happen without all
these pieces if we're not having
philosophers in conversation with the
statisticians then this synthesis can't
happen now maybe the synthesis that you
care about doesn't need that but
we care about this and this synthesis
requires it so we need to develop the
approaches and the communication around
that and um so it's uh really a tip of
the spear effort even apart from the
consequences of the research
what a heartwarming sentiment thank you
for sharing that I I think
I love the phrase epistemic hygiene
because that is so crucial I think to
every field but it's like particularly
aggressively exposed in this field which
is exactly why I think that
um
my science has has benefited so
powerfully from close collaboration with
philosophers and with statisticians I
mean this is kind of the space that I I
live in here in the cognitive Sciences
department is where we're halfway
between Ai and philosophy and Psychology
and Neuroscience and engineering and
it's like it it's kind of like where all
these things come together but then this
meta science thing I'm happy that you
picked up on that
um because I think that it's also really
the the bibliometric analyzes are really
critical and
we're at this crazy spot and have been
for a long time now but I think it's
really really coming to a head
where the vast majority of our
scientific knowledge is not accessible
to anyone researchers simply because
there's so much of it
right you can't read all of the
literature you can't even read all the
literature that's in your tiny little
corner and
Consciousness science like many other
fields in this way actually is one of
those that brings together a lot of
different fields so it makes it even
harder for you to keep up with the
things that are going to be really
relevant I mean you have to keep up with
The Cutting Edge tools in neuroimaging
data analysis plus the epistemic hygiene
that the philosophers are going to bring
plus like Cutting Edge behavioral
paradigms and what they mean and like
you know naturalistic data uh collection
settings so that you're not just saying
oh I've discovered something fundamental
about Consciousness by showing you Gabor
patches all day and I say this as
someone who shows people Gabor patches
all day but it's it's really like it's a
real challenge to bring together all
these things and maybe you're right
maybe that Consciousness science is I
don't know about the canary in the cold
mine so to speak but maybe you're right
that
it's one of the places where you can
really see all these cogs working
together to come at one major question
or maybe you don't
quite see the need for that hygiene and
some other fields yet it still is there
like latent cause analysis is not just
something that we do in Consciousness
science or Neuroscience we do it in
economics we do it in sociology we do it
like everywhere and so having a real
handle on how to design stuff that
actually asks the questions that you're
interested in is something that
I find that I have to continuously work
hard to keep in my sights
um and and I'm lucky that we've got a
pile of philosophers that we get to hang
out with who
blow into your talk and say everything
that you just said is wrong and here's
why here's this logical hole in what
you've done and they're right
and it's great because it makes the
science better
and you don't typically get philosophers
you know blowing into a talk in a lot of
other fields it doesn't happen
and um and I think it should
we all have that inroad
to our experience
so it is something that integrates
across disciplines kind of even casts
the disciplinary organizational Paradigm
into
um at least critical light and and then
um goes even outside of Academia because
these are these are what people
search engine for and uh language model
discuss and I think it is one of these
um it's like an itch that some can't
scratch with this inscrutable and
ineffable nature that that does Verge
into the mystical and then like so what
do we do with the huge mystery
and and so that that makes it a um a a
training and exhibition fields
um again that's not just important but
like is kind of the the
um
the archetype of well how do you have a
multi-decade conversation
with potentially non-compatible
theorizing
whereas in many of the physical sciences
including physical reductionist
perspectives on on neuroscience
threads open and close a little bit
quicker a little bit easier tend to not
um delve into ancient history tend to
not need to invoke World Knowledge
Traditions so that
makes it fun it makes it fun and useful
and if something's fun and useful what
what secret third thing are we looking
for exactly sounds like uh if you
weren't already a Consciousness
scientist maybe we've converted you
um as as only a bug doctor I did did uh
one one work on the uh ant colony and
definitions of Consciousness and we
didn't come down on the issue of weather
like the nest mates are conscious under
what definition or the colony
um but more pointed out well if you
define it according to some neuro
mammalian neuroanatomy then you kind of
already know what the answer is going to
be it's going to be no and if you define
it according to a specific
um primate censored symbolic
communication approach again you know
what that's going to be it's no if you
define it based upon some generic
informational property
then you already know what it's going to
be it's going to be on that continuum
and so we kind of tried to flip the
approach by instead of asking like in
which
um
teacher would help us differentiate
whether the ant colony is conscious or
not we just said let's just look at what
the features that people are using and
then ask whether colony is but but we
don't have we don't have the um one
meter metal bar for Consciousness so
again it's like well let's say 7 out of
10 that we observed we don't know how
many other unproposed theories there are
so 7 out of 10 could be total
um uh sampling bias
um even if it was 10 or 10 then what
would that type of consensus really mean
and um
that's where our road took us
and I I saw that conclusion as like
a chance to broaden the discussion
but discussions are not only about
broadening because there's real
decisions that are being made so it
can't only be
yes and and I think that when you
connect it back to falsification and all
of these other properties that's where
we get the the winnowing but it's those
two complementary conversations like the
broader
um inclusion of perspectives that
expands the space that we can comprehend
and then the diligence that that also
shrinks it back down and somehow will
zigzag to better and better
understandings
your uh your point about
we don't have a yardstick we don't have
a metal rod right that says you know how
conscious I mean like according to to
some folks we we have that metal rod and
we've surpassed that with for example
large language models
uh they're uh and we're not just talking
you know particular Google Engineers who
decide to get really excited about how
their pad language model gets is
conscious we're talking
any any kind of reasonable
interpretation of the old school Turing
test
would be passed by existing language
models right now in fact arguably it
might have been passed long ago with
Eliza
uh in like the 70s
um and and if it wasn't passed with
Eliza then certainly it has been passed
now but I think that there is a growing
understanding that information
processing capacity and intelligence are
not the same thing as internal
phenomenal experience
and that the tests that we have to the
extent that we have any tests at all are
willfully inadequate
and as you said are locked to particular
implementations so you can't apply the
mammalian test for Consciousness like oh
I'm looking for this particular neural
signature which tells me whether the
monkey is anesthetized or not I can't
apply that to ants and expect it to work
it's not going to tell me anything
useful there can't necessarily apply it
to octopuses either for the record so
we're not even going insects we're going
other arguably incredibly intelligent
beings that can open jars and be sneaky
and like do all sorts of cool stuff
and uh and that have complex social
interactions
and are basically aliens this is my my
you know professional scientific opinion
here what they basically are right like
they're so fundamentally physically
different from us
and so any consciousness of meter that
we develop for us or that applies in
monkeys or even in dogs or cats is not
really going to apply there
um and so differentiating tests for
intelligence from tests from like inner
experience it's a really difficult
problem
and then there's the third problem which
is a test for whether we attribute
Consciousness to an agent which if you
saw a movie X Machina is the Garland
test
um so that's like you know do never mind
whether it actually has Consciousness do
I attribute Consciousness to it because
that is going to change how we interact
with it and the rights that we ascribe
to it and so on and so I think we're
well past the point at which we need to
get a better handle on this some of the
stuff that I'm working on right now is
moving in this direction not just me and
a huge group of lots of other people
um and I think Joshua bengio gave
testimony to Congress like today uh
about the need for uh increased
regulatory oversight of uh who has
access to so-called artificial
intelligence models so that we can
better understand
how their implementation and their
interaction with humans might exacerbate
biases or cause all sorts of other
problems
um so you can actually go and read his
his testimony that he gave I don't
remember whether the link is you can
find it
um but he had a summary and then he
links to the testimony and I think that
having folks like yahshua and other
Giants in the field speaking out about
the need for
actually tackling this and not this
isn't just a philosopher's playground to
talk about Consciousness this is
this is as you said it's a testing bed
for where the rest of science is going
and it's also like very topical right
now
so what is that
healthy
conversation looked like in the case of
the synthetic intelligences and language
models and all of this
um
what what does that continue to look
like between the actual measures and
proxies that we use in research and uh I
mean what memes or themes or words that
I guess by definition aren't popular
today like big data wasn't Popular until
it was so what some something like what
has to come on the scene and come into
the lab do you think to support the kind
of
um like work and knowledge that that
either of you would want to see
thank you
this isn't an answer to your question
but it just reminded me of one thing
that we need less of is people writing
about these interactions with AI that
are like my AI told me that it wanted to
get married or like my AI whatever like
that's not it's not useful it's not news
stop reporting about it
that's all I have to say okay go ahead
no I I wanted you to take this too
because I think that the question is
about
Communication in a way that is you're
you're much more embedded in the science
communication space than I am and so for
I think one possible way to go about
this that maybe you can speak to would
be what kinds of you know you're Daniel
you're talking about what do we need to
bring into the lab and maybe
communication tools is one of those or
ways of communicating this science ways
of of end to different audiences
um and so maybe Nora you've got some
ideas even if you've done so much in
this space I don't know
yeah I mean I guess I what we've been
talking about with people who study
human consciousness
um
people who study Consciousness and other
entities as well like just being clear
about what you mean by Consciousness
like do you mean a subjective experience
do you mean
um you know basically is a light on or
off like uh do you mean awake versus
asleep
um
just being really clear about what level
you're talking at I think is really
helpful again when you're just like
presenting your research whether it's on
Twitter or you're talking to a
journalist
um really being clear-cut about that so
that people can't make kind of
extrapolations from your work that your
work doesn't cover
um
I don't know what else I mean
yeah I guess just being willing to also
talk about your work I feel like a lot
of data science feels pretty
inaccessible to the general public
um so finding ways to communicate what
you do and how you're conducting your
work is helpful being open about it
yeah there's a lot of jargon in our
field too in any field there's jargon um
but the the oversimplification this is
going back to what we talked about at
the beginning the oversimplification of
jargoning terms in our field seems
particularly susceptible to
uh
creating a situation where the the facts
haven't changed but the interpretation
has
uh and so I think
it's almost like sensitivity training
for anybody who's in this space like
just kind of a you know a little a
tutorial that you can do that's like a
two hour you know click-through thing
it's like here are all the ways in which
communicating this type of science due
to its nature is
more challenging than you might
anticipate and so my my own involvement
in um
in a program run by the Canadian
Institute for advanced research has
given me a little bit of training and
speaking with the media and I would
never never say that I am an expert in
this at all uh I will only say that uh
it was eye-opening and it was very
useful and the clarity of language that
you are used to using the the Precision
of language that you're used to using in
a close scientific sphere versus when
you're speaking to a more General
audience and when you're speaking to a
journalist or with several journalists
who are then going to be writing for a
more General audience it's a it's a
different mindset it's a different way
of speaking
and even just being aware of that I
think is really really useful it's not
that one is better than the other it's
just that they are very different and
that when we are training to be
scientists when we're doing a PhD in a
field related to this
speaking to the general public is not a
skill that gets pressed on
it's not a skill that gets it's part of
like your professional development
training maybe you do like one practice
talk somewhere but it's not typically
part of a general training protocol and
So speaking to non-specialists speaking
to the media is speaking to high school
audiences speaking to your mom at the
dinner table like learning how to do
this effectively can actually be really
valuable and really rewarding and really
powerful and again I would never say
that I am an expert at this at this
point I just like to think that I'm a
little better at it than I otherwise
would be had I not had it drilled into
me how careful I need to be
I would also say
um don't be scared to like email
journalists if you see that something's
inaccurate or you know speak up like
Megan has done
um about the kind of how things are
portrayed inaccurately because yeah as a
journalist like no one's ever done that
to me but it would if something wasn't
accurate I would want to know and I
would want to fix it like ASAP so don't
feel bad about emailing journalists they
want their pieces to be accurate as well
so
that's what I would add that can add to
the conversation yeah it does make me
feel a little bad about like you know
calling out the pieces that I did in in
the presentation in the the piece of
writing that I did too but at the same
time like they put this in writing and
this is wrong and and it's
I I don't like making people upset and I
don't like making people angry
um but
it's out there in the world and I saw a
million eyeballs and that's a problem
and so we're hoping your viewership is
about a million right Daniel so give or
take and so no Brilliance for everybody
so this will cover everybody who read
those those articles right
it's it's
interesting like the field is about
awareness of
other Minds our own mind but also
awareness of other minds and in theory
but then in practice awareness of other
Minds is communication because if we say
something that it's like well I wouldn't
be annoyed by that or I wouldn't be
angry with that but it's like but you
missed the point of communication which
it's not about what you would think
about it it's about because the
recipient would be so it's kind of like
the theory and the practice of of
um situational awareness about different
Minds all of which are different than
our own some are potentially radically
different than our own others might be
more similar
um so it's there's really
um maybe even a quintessential
relationship between
Consciousness studies and communication
studies which provides like a really
unique two-way street
that that
um the world is swerving into that to
Lane Highway with these questions that
are grabbing people's salience
what what are your sort of um like
closing thoughts or directions or what
are some exciting areas that that you'd
like to
see unfolding in the coming months and
years
well I'll go first
yeah first of all I
I think I
communicating conscious to science being
about knowing about other Minds I mean
it's like effective communication is
theory of mind and theory of mine may
have a lot to do with modeling other
minds and modeling your own mind and yes
absolutely it's all it's all wrapped up
so
I think for me
um getting this right going forward or
continuing to to work towards getting it
right is a priority for me
uh and one of the the pieces
scientifically that I'm working on that
I hope to then communicate effectively
when we get it right or several of the
pieces is I have a couple
um these really wonderful large
collaborative projects where we're
working on everything from figuring out
how you would actually measure of
Consciousness effectively or what it
might even take to measure Consciousness
effectively in other entities that are
not necessarily like awake behaving and
healthy adult human beings uh all the
way to Let's actually design some
experiments to test several different
theories of Consciousness let's design a
new uh some of what Nora's working on
actually is designing new measurement
approaches to say well we need to
actually like have a quantitative handle
on the things that we're talking about
so this becomes objective it becomes
falsifiable and becomes like we can do
model arbitration so all these things
I'm really excited about but overarching
all of those is this idea of
going it's all connected right you've
talked about how Consciousness science
might be this this Leading Edge or wave
front of how uh interdisciplinary
science and meta science needs to be
done going forward as
uh as we become even more Theory driven
in some of our uh scientific lines of
inquiry than we have been in the past
and more interested in latent variables
and causal Discovery and so on and so
forth and as the science teams get
bigger
and more complicated and the jobs within
those science teams become more
specialized and we have more and more
need for interdisciplinary collaboration
we're gonna have to change How We Do
team science and how we do credit
assignment within team science in a way
that I think might end up being kind of
incompatible with the nice siled cute
departmental structure that we have in
our universities
uh and so
a focus on not just tolerating but
celebrating interdisciplinarity
celebrating team science doing credit
assignment correctly and you know saying
first author isn't the only thing that
matters that like it really matters if
you wrote this gorgeous software package
that facilitated a whole bunch of stuff
like that's also a meaningful and
Powerful contribution even if you didn't
get first author on that paper you still
deserve a lot of credit so I think that
there's a lot of shaking up that we need
to do about how we do science going
forward and I really like the idea of
using Consciousness science as a case
study I think that's beautiful and thank
you very much for making that lovely
connection because it really locks
together a lot of the things that I've
been thinking about recently as well so
there's my my parting
it's a
yeah I was also going to bring up the
um
these huge projects that you're a part
of and that other people are part of
it's really exciting to see so many
people working together in these huge
teams I feel like it just makes science
so much more efficient and more careful
so that's very cool
another thing I'm hoping is that one the
journalists don't get scared of covering
Consciousness science from this I think
like we'll learn from our mistakes and
we'll move forward I I don't think we'll
get scared but I hope that there's more
coverage of this field
um and I also hope that I mean something
that I've noticed about science
journalism is they really like to just
have clear-cut findings because that's
the simplest thing to communicate to
people but I think we can as a society
like learn to be comfortable with the
ambiguity a little bit more
um especially when it comes to conscious
science like we might have found
something but we're not sure and that's
okay and that's science like it's okay
if your headline isn't Snappy and
clear it's important for it to be clear
but snappy and I guess
have one takeaway point it's okay if it
doesn't have a takeaway point
um yeah I think that's what I'm excited
about
New Era of science journalism
well it sounds like
bigger teams bigger Community more
Theory more data more philosophy more
ambiguity
it'll be a great time
more philosophy more ambiguity love it
yes
thank you Megan and Nora for joining
always
um welcome back so
till next time yeah thank you so much
this has been really a pleasure thanks
for having us
thank you bye
[Music]